Today we're going to learn Bubble Sort.
Here's what we'll do.
We're going to compare consecutive items.
If they're out of place, we'll swap them.
The highest number will bubble its way to the right with each iteration.
A sorted partition will form at the end of the array.
It's pretty simple, so I'll be quiet and let you watch.
Let's see how it works.
Done with the first iteration.
9 is now in the correct spot. Let's continue.
You get the picture. I'll see you at the end of the algorithm.
We're done. Our array is sorted.
Here's the pseudocode for Bubble Sort.
As you can guess from the nested for loop, the worst case time complexity is O of n squared, where n is the size of the array.
If you have questions, please ask them below. Thank you for watching.