Today we're going to learn merge sort.
A few quick points, then we'll get to the example.
Merge sort is usually done recursively.
When you think of merge sort, as with other recursive algorithms, I want you to think of divide and conquer.
We're going to break our problem into smaller problems in order to solve it.
Let's get started. We have the following array and we want it sorted.
We're going to continuously split the array in half, our divide step.
Until we are left with the individual items.
Watch and see.
Our array is now broken down into individual items.
One note before we start sorting. When you implement this in code, these steps will be done in a different order because of recursion.
But I think this human friendly order provides more clarity in learning.
Let's continue. We're ready to sort.
We'll examine the individual items, compare their values, and merge them into temporary arrays.
The temporary arrays are sorted, but there's work left to do. Let's jump up the recursion stack and continue.
We merge our smaller arrays into a larger one, inserting items in the correct order.
We'll use the same array again.
We'll merge our larger arrays into a larger one, inserting items in the correct order.
One more merge and we'll have our sorted array.
And that's it. Our array is now sorted.
Here's the pseudocode for merge sort. On the left you have the recursive part, which halves the arrays.
On the right is the merge function which combines the arrays.
Merge sort has a worst case time complexity of O of n times log n.
The easiest way to think about it is to start with the merge step.
Looking at the while loop, we see we have to visit n items.
The log n comes from the maximum height of a binary tree we create, which is on the order of log n.
Thank you for watching. Please comment suggestions for future videos below, as well as any questions you may have.